[Music]
sam harris and jordan Peterson had these
four debates over the summer you were
the moderator of two of those in
Vancouver what do you think was achieved
in them where do you think the kind of
lack of alignment is still and where do
you think this debate is I think a lot
was accomplished in Vancouver and I'm
less intimately familiar with what took
place in London and Dublin but in
Vancouver we started out with two people
who did not really know how much to
trust each other and although they
didn't arrive in the same place I
believe they did come to a mutual
respect and even affection for each
other that as far as I know persists to
this day I think for each of them there
is a vindication in the distance that
they traveled and then there's a bitter
pill and it's obviously much easier to
accept a vindication and a bitter pill
and so the real question is what in the
end will become of the two bitter pills
that they each have to face in Sam's
case the vindication is that in fact the
universe does not need some divine
entity to explain any of the phenomena
that we see on the other hand the
dismissal of people's religious beliefs
as miss being misinformed or as a
misunderstanding of the universe is
obviously not entirely satisfactory
these belief systems do appear to be the
product of forces that have shaped them
for a purpose essentially to benefit the
people who - who hold these beliefs so
Sam is grappling with the implications
of that in effect it is a challenge to a
simple new atheist perspective Jordan is
in the situation of having a vindication
of his belief that these myths in which
he has argued that there is a
deal of meaning are in fact what he says
they are they are a kind of wisdom and
they are profoundly important in human
history for him the bitter pill is that
they are not timeless there is no magic
formula that would imbue them with the
ability to tell us what we should do in
novel circumstances because these myths
are the product of adaptive evolution
they are limited in utility to the
circumstances in which they evolved and
because we live in circumstances that
don't look anything like the situation
of thousands of years ago we should be
suspect of these stories and their
relevance to our modern problems so I
think this has yet to play out and it
will be interesting to see where Jordan
and Sam end up wrestling with these
things going forward but the fact that
they can hear each other now and even to
the point on the second night in
Vancouver of being able to properly
steel man each other's position I think
is tremendous progress and you mentioned
about the archetypes so Peterson's
frames those as kind of pre-existing
categories of being and you're saying
that they cannot possibly be
pre-existing categories of being well
they can be to an extent but there is a
shorthand that we use when we teach
evolution and what we say is that
evolution adapts creatures to their
environment that is not what it does
evolution adapts creatures to the
environments of their ancestors and it
the reason it looks like it adapts
creatures to their environment is the
environments of one's ancestor tends to
look like the environment that you find
yourself in but there are lots of places
in evolutionary history where that's not
true
where a creature disperses over a divide
or where something changes so that
whatever was true for the ancestor is
not true for the descendant we modern
humans are in this circumstance in a way
that is arguably unprecedented
technology has rendered the entire
landscape novel and so it's not that
there will be no element in all of the
mythology that carries over to this day
but overwhelmingly there will be a
mismatch between those myths and our
modern circumstances so from the
perspective of should we treat them as
god-given and learn from them no if ever
there was a time not to do that this is
that time it's interesting you're
talking about archetypes because I think
quite a lot of people have a sense that
there's something about Jordan Peterson
that's backward looking even though the
details of when they question that when
he's kind of described as the custodian
of the patriarchy or whatever the detail
of of that is usually a
misrepresentation but that there is at
least an aspect of him that's that's
backward facing in terms of trying to
recover old archetypes rather than say
we could use these to create new ways of
looking at the world well hey I do see
some aspect of Jordan as
backward-looking
I think the image of him that is
portrayed is way off you know he is an
interesting mixture of traditional
perspectives and very modern perspective
so you know in a way he's a little bit
hard to to properly paint there's also I
would argue a real value in an
authoritative voice putting the brakes
on the embrace of everything new it's
not to say that I think we can live in
the world that I think Jordan probably
expects would be best for us I think
that's an untenable solution to our
problems however I also think a headlong
rush into everything shiny and new is a
mistake and so in a way Jordan has
carved out the role of of Orthodoxy and
to the extent that he now comes to a
perspective that recognizes the limits
of the inherited wisdom and says well we
need to cautiously look forward and
figure out what we're gonna do now that
we know that our myths are very very
noisy relative to our circumstances if
he does that people will hear it in a
way that they can't hear it from
somebody who's so enthusiastic about
what's novel that
they erode their own credibility I think
Peterson is restoring a burden of proof
that is correct the burden of proof says
do not change that which works unless
you have a very good reason the
architecture we've been handed is less
and less functional so there's more and
more reason to face the hazard of change
because we simply can't stick with what
we've got but it is important to have a
force pulling in the direction of not
throwing out functional architecture so
that when you do throw it out you know
why and you are sober about the costs
you're going to pay for starting with a
blank sheet of paper and I mean it's
been said before that evolution is
essentially conservative that it
conserves it builds on what's gone
before and Jordan Peterson users
evolution quite a lot in his
construction his arguments as a has an
11 area biologist how what do you make
of that does he do it well he does it
extremely well for a psychologist and I
will say as much as I would love to see
a landscape populated by people who
think about human evolution who outshine
him by virtue of the amount of time they
spent on the question I don't see many
of those he's quite good at it but there
is a place where his argument runs out
of steam and he continues to go with it
there's a place in which he wants to
find a timelessness and maybe a
particular priority for certain myths
over alternative myths that is not
justified by evolutionary logic
evolutionary logic says essentially the
longer a particular piece of wisdom has
stood the more likely it is to remain
relevant into the future but we're still
stuck with myths that come to us from
several thousand years back and the
world of several thousand years ago is
one that not only is dissimilar from our
world but in many ways is opposite the
ability of human beings for example to
damage their
through technology it existed several
thousand years in the past but it was
nothing compared to our current ability
to destroy the world out from under us
using technologies that even placed the
destruction at a remove so we're not
even aware of second place and you
mentioned before about Sam Harris and
New Atheism
you do you think that's an even more
bitter pill to swallow ah I think the
problem for New Atheism is perhaps more
difficult because the people who have
been most enthusiastic about New Atheism
have been very public about their
beliefs and their beliefs distilled down
to something very simple which turns out
to be incomplete there is no God in the
sky who cares about human affairs and is
meddling in them that much is true
but the fact that believers are not
delusional is that's a rather large
correction for one's worldview so I
think there is a way in which having
been very public about a very simple
story the transition to a more nuanced
story is is difficult and you'll saying
very confidently that it's not
delusional weddy what do you base that
on the fact that were belief in deities
and the supernatural maladaptive because
these things are held culturally it
would be very easy to take the software
program that runs in the heads of a
particular population and edit out that
fraction which was simply wrong in fact
there's always disagreement within any
religious tradition about which portions
of the sacred to esteem and which
portions to to down-regulate
that is the fodder for selection to
function that means that anything that
we see persistently being passed on
generation after generation must be
paying its cost and then some
because it's paying its cost and then
some regarding it as an error is just
simply a mistake so this is the very
same kind of logic that Darwin used for
physiological traits he was sent an
orchid from Madagascar that had a very
long nectar tube and reasoned that there
must be a moth out there with a - with a
tongue that long or else it would not
make sense for the flower to have
invested in this structure after his
death the moth became known to Western
science my point is that logic simply
extends into the cultural realm and it
very clearly applies to extremely
expensive sets of beliefs that come
along with the major religions of the
world we know they pay their freight
because if they didn't it's all too easy
to edit out the part that's just baggage
and where do you think this conversation
goes now do you think there's any sense
in another debate between Jordan and Sam
what do you think they've they've
concluded it well I think the debate is
not so much between Jordan and Sam
anymore I think what they have done is
they have established the landscape in
which this debate takes place in to the
extent that either one of them alters
their position enough to change what we
can see that's great
on the other hand now that they've
explored the territory I think it's also
open for others to join in and talk to
either one of them were talk without
them present and really the question is
just like it is in any scientific
exploration somebody discovers that
there's a set of phenomena to understand
and then others come in and define the
details of what they find there that's
quite natural so if they're enthusiastic
about having more discussions I'd love
to see him but even if they weren't I
don't think you know it it means that
things have stalled out it just means
we've been shown where the discussion is
and now it's time to have it where would
you place yourself between Jordan and
Sam well I actually had a discussion
with Sam about this very thing and I
think
said it was clear to him in the same way
it is clear to me that I was actually
dead center between them in perspective
which I you know it's it's just luck
that that's the case because my position
arose before I had any idea what their
positions were but it happens that an
evolutionary perspective on the
evolution of faith suggests that these
myths have a meaning that it isn't
timeless and I don't know that put me
right between them both in a physical
sense and philosophically mm-hmm and you
you describe yourself as an atheist do
you have a conception of the sacred does
that word mean anything oh absolutely I
do find sometimes one has to redefine
words in order to get the value out of
them and I've probably redefined sacred
a bit I don't call myself an atheist I
think almost anybody who tried to
evaluate my belief system would probably
come to the conclusion that that's what
I am but I've actually been made so
uncomfortable by the simplicity of new
atheism that my feeling is I can't even
afford that saying atheist is now taking
sides in a debate where I'm not on one
of these sides I would like to be
completely hard-headed about what is
true in the universe but I do not want
to back people into a corner whose
beliefs arise through an evolutionary
process so I hope one day that this
particular discussion has had the stigma
taken out of it so that it is
comfortable to embrace atheism as no
more than a description of what is true
about phenomena in the universe that it
doesn't carry an ideological component
that as long as it carries an
ideological component I'm cautious about
saying that about myself so I mean
that's why you chose the word sacred
because for a new atheist that word
would be meaningless so if it's not
meaningless for you what what does it
mean and
well I see a a spectrum that runs from
what I call the sacred to what I call
the shamanistic and really this is a
spectrum of caution or would be caution
about change there are some things that
are so essential to basic function that
you upend them as a last resort and
there are other things that you upend
either because they don't have profound
implications or because they simply
don't function as they are and you must
change them so my sense is that we have
a kind of distinction between the sorts
of matters that we hand over to a
priestly class the sacred these are
things you don't upend willy-nilly and
the shamanistic stuff which is open to
interpretation that is open to you know
to hunches to following a thread and
seeing where it leads
so the sacred is simply that stuff which
is so fundamental to function that one
ought not tinker casually hmm and the
shamanistic shamanistic is that which is
up for tinkering either because the
implications aren't profound or because
the implications are profound and what
you've been handed is no longer
functional Brett thank you very much
you're very welcome
you